Finding Aid for Second Baptist Church (Detroit, Mich.) Records, 1911-1989
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Second Baptist Church (Detroit, Mich.) Records 1911-1989, 1926-1988
Second Baptist Church (Detroit, Mich.)
1 folder of photographs
14 microfilm reels
Oldest African American church in Michigan; administrative records, papers of individual pastors, church publications.
90121 Ba/2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The church allowed the library to microfilm its records in 1989-1990. Donor no. 7617. The original records are held by the church.
The collection is open for research.
Second Baptist Church (Detroit, Mich.) is the oldest Black church in Michigan. It was founded in 1836 when thirteen former slaves broke with First Baptist of Detroit over the issue of paying dues to a church which would not let Blacks vote on church matters. Second Baptist prides itself on its stability and longevity; it is the oldest Black church that continues to serve downtown Detroit. This stability owes much to the breadth of vision of capable pastors beginning with the first pastor, William Monroe, continuing through Supply Chase during the Civil War, and extending to the twentieth century tenures of Robert Bradby and A.A. Banks. Second Baptist leaders saw the mission of the church going beyond the spiritual needs of the congregation, extending to efforts to secure political, economic, and social freedom and equality for Blacks. In the nineteenth century, these efforts were manifested in the church's serving as a station on the underground railroad, hosting Frederick Douglass and John Brown, and twice hosting conventions to secure suffrage for Blacks in Michigan. In the twentieth century, these efforts were evident in Bradby's securing jobs (often at Ford Motor Co.) for immigrant Blacks in the 1920s and 1930s, in the social services provided by the Frances Harper Inn for Employed Girls, and in the support of Martin Luther King, Jr.'s Montgomery Improvement Association. Second Baptist's stability, able leadership, and freedom seeking social activism combined to create a well-defined sense of the historical significance of the church.
The sense of historical importance has been preserved by Second Baptist despite fires in 1854, 1916 and 1917 which evidently destroyed much of the historical record for the church in the nineteenth century. Fortunately the strong oral tradition and the edifice of the church itself preserved some of the highlights of the early years. Second Baptist's crucial role as a station on the underground railroad was well remembered and amply evidenced by basement rooms reserved to hide fugitive slaves. With the church's pastors serving as station masters and member George De Baptiste often providing ferry service to Windsor, it has been estimated that Second Baptist aided four to five thousand former slaves in gaining their freedom. Given that freedom was so valued, it is not surprising that Second Baptist member, William Webb, was host to a meeting of Frederick Douglass, John Brown, De Baptiste, and others who planned the emancipation of slaves shortly before John Brown's heroic and doomed raid on the Harper's Ferry armory. Second Baptist also hosted the Concerned Colored Citizens of Detroit in 1843 and 1865; these meetings resulted in a call for universal suffrage to include Black men. Both calls were unheeded by the Michigan legislature.
The twentieth-century history of Second Baptist is better documented and is very much shaped by the pastors who guided the flock through the challenging and rewarding times of peace and war, prosperity and poverty, growth and retrenchment. The first of the two monumental figures to stand at the helm of Second Baptist was Robert L. Bradby, pastor from 1910 until his death in 1946. Bradby was committed to doing missionary work among the sick, the poor, and the unemployed in Detroit. He was equally devoted to preserving Second Baptist as the downtown haven for both established Black Detroiters and the new migrants drawn north by manufacturing jobs after 1916. This missionary zeal, growth in Detroit's Black population due to migration, and Bradby's ability to link men and jobs led to a rapid growth in the size of the congregation. Second Baptist had never had more than 300 members in the 1800s; under Bradby this number rose to 1000 by 1920 and 3000 by 1930. Many of these new members were drawn by Bradby's spirited revivals; other were attracted by the various lay groups which reached out to the local community. With this growth came a concomitant rise the congregation's influence in Detroit and in the national Black community.
With Bradby's sudden death in 1946, Second Baptist was faced with the difficult task of finding a pastor capable of leading a large congregation and guiding the growth of the church. A.A. Banks was just the man to fill the bill. Like Bradby, Banks coupled a missionary zeal "to win the unsaved and to teach the saved" with a strong sense of organization. The former attribute (and a second wave of Black migration after World War II) accounted for the continued growth of Second Baptist. Membership reached 4000 by 1950, peaked at 4800 in the early 1950s, before drifting back toward 4000 by 1970. Banks developed a group fellowship system which broke the congregation down into 48 groups of 100 so that individual members could feel a closer sense of community within the whole church. Banks, noting that his congregation was aging (as was Banks), devoted much time and energy in his later years to developing youth organizations which he hoped would link the young people of Second Baptist more closely to the church. At the time of Banks' death in 1977 this continued to be a concern.
Robert Holloman took over the reins of Second Baptist in 1978. Almost immediately friction developed between the new pastor and the deacons and trustees. After a bitter, public, and protracted conflict, including court actions, Holloman was forced to step down as pastor in June 1982. Second Baptist, faced with declining numbers of members, an aging congregation, and anxious to put the bitter Holloman affair behind them, selected William Epps as pastor. Unfortunately for Second Baptist, Epps found that his calling was a California ministry. In 1988, for the third time in ten years, the church selected a new pastor, Kevin Turman.
Pastors of Second Baptist Church
1836-1846 William C. Monroe
1847 William P. Newman
1848-1851 Samuel H. Davis
1851-1856 D.G. Lett
1857-1859 William Troy
1860-1861 O.W. Anderson
1861-1874 Supply Chase
1874-1876 Thomas F. Scott
1876-1881 John P. Wills
1882-1883 W.R. Davis
1883-1886 W.A. Burch
1886-1887 R.H. Porter
1888-1891 E.H. McDonald
1891-1892 N.H. McBayne
1893-1896 A.D. Chandler
1896-1901 W.S. Bradden
1902-1905 Holland Powell
1906-1910 William Jones
1910-1946 Robert L. Bradby, Sr.
1947-1977 Allan A. Banks, Jr.
1978-1982 Robert F. Holloman, Jr.
1983-1987 William S. Epps
1988- Kevin M. Turman
The records of Second Baptist comprise 14 reels of microfilm (representing 6 linear feet of manuscript material) and 1 folder of photographs. The extant materials are arranged in four series: Administration, Pastors' Papers, Publications, and Photographs.
This record group thoroughly documents Second Baptist's efforts to tend to both the spiritual and physical needs of Black Detroiters since the 1920s. The Administration, Pastors' Papers, Publications, and Photographs series reflect, respectively, the internal workings of the church, the private efforts of the pastors over time, and the publicly presented external face of Second Baptist. The microfilm (representing 6 linear feet of manuscript material) consists of annual reports, financial records, histories, minutes of advisory board meetings, pastoral correspondence, annual and quarterly publications, and weekly bulletins. There is also a scattering of photographs. The work of Second Baptist before the 1920s is visible retrospectively in histories and reminiscences sanctioned by the church in the 1930s. The records of the church for the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries were evidently destroyed in the fires of 1916 and 1917.
Subjects:
Afro-American churches.; Afro-Americans--Employment.; Afro-Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; Baptists, Black--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.)--Church history.; Ford Motor Company.; Second Baptist Church (Detroit, Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Material:
Afro-American churches.; Afro-Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; Churches--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.)--Churches.; Second Baptist Church (Detroit, Mich.)
Contributors:
Banks, A. A. (Allan A.); Bradby, Robert L.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Administration 1919-1988
  The Administration group was created in the course of processing and consists of those records related to the structure and organization of the church. This group, arranged alphabetically by type of material, runs just over one linear foot and includes annual reports, constitutions, financial records, histories, and minutes. The histories are valuable in providing self-reflective views of Second Baptist as a church very concerned with its place in history. The financial records are fulsome and quite detailed, so they provide telling insights into the challenges facing Second Baptist during the lean years of the Depression and the boom times of postwar Detroit. The annual reports and minutes of the advisory board and trustees are quite illuminative of the 1970s and 1980s as the church faced the challenges of an aging congregation grown fewer in number and the court controversy surrounding the removal of Pastor Holloman.
  - Annual Reports 1984-1988 (Reel 1)
  - Constitutions 1949, 1979 (Reel 1)
  - Financial 1924-1984
    - Treasurer's reports 1924-1962 (Reel 1)
    - Deacon's contributions 1957-1965 (Reel 1)
    - Members (noncontributing) 1966 (Reel 1)
    - Members' contributions 1964, 1970 (Reel 1)
    - Treasurer's reports 1978-1984 (Reel 2)
  - Histories 1940-1988 (Reel 2)
  - Members Manual 1985 (Reel 2)
  - Minutes (Advisory Board and Trustees) 1974-1988 (Reel 2)
  - Special Collections 1926-1983
    - Articles of Incorporation 1926, 1952 (Reel 2)
    - Histories 1926-1983 (Reel 2)
  - Wedding Notebooks 1919-1988
    - Bradby, Moody, and McNeil 1919-1934 (Reel 2)
    - Banks, Lewis, Simmons, Holmes, Macy, Holloman, and Epps 1951-1988 (Reel 2)
- Pastors' Papers 1911-1988
  (primarily 1926-1982)
  The Pastors' Papers group comprises two linear feet and consists primarily of correspondence, reports to the pastor, and other materials related to the pastor's specific responsibilities. The materials within this group are first arranged chronologically according to the tenure of the pastor and then alphabetically by type. The bulk of materials within this group consists of the correspondence of Pastors Bradby and Banks. The eight folders of Bradby correspondence are an unusually rich source on Black Detroit history. They reflect his efforts to tend to the social and economic needs of his congregation through securing jobs (often at Ford) and housing for deserving church members. The more extensive Banks correspondence reflects a deep and abiding concern for the physical (as well as the spiritual) needs of his Second Baptist flock. Unfortunately these revealing runs of correspondence are incomplete: there are years missing for Bradby, Banks' correspondence for many years consists only of copies of his responses, and the pastoral correspondence of Epps and Turman is painfully thin.
  - Robert L. Bradby 1911-1982
    (primarily 1926-1944)
    - Associate Pastor reports (McNeil and Moody) 1925-1926 (Reel 3)
    - Bradby Collection 1911-1982
      - Anniversaries 1911-1945 (Reel 3)
      - Biographical materials 1946 (Reel 3)
      - Memorials 1946-1982 (Reel 3)
    - Correspondence 1925-1944 (Reel 3)
    - Deacons' Board 1926-1944 (Reel 3)
    - Missionary/Social worker (Reid) 1925-1928 (Reel 3)
    - Newspaper clipping 1922 (Reel 3)
  - A. A. Banks, Jr. 1944-1982
    (primarily 1947-1977)
    - Anniversaries 1972-1973 (Reel 3)
    - Associate Pastor reports (Lewis and Macy) 1960-1961 (Reel 3)
    - Correspondence 1944-1957 (Reel 3)
    - Correspondence 1958-February 1968 (Reel 4)
    - Correspondence March 1968-1977 (Reel 5)
    - Missionary/Sick reports 1970-1982 (Reel 5)
    - Newspaper clippings 1950-1977 (Reel 5)
    - Women's Day preparations 1954, 1960-1974 (Reel 5)
  - Robert F. Holloman, Jr. 1978-1982
    - Correspondence 1978-January 1979 (Reel 5)
    - Correspondence February 1979-1981 (Reel 6)
    - Holloman Collection (regarding his dismissal) 1980-1982 (Reel 6)
    - Newspaper clippings 1978-1982 (Reel 6)
  - William S. Epps 1983-1986
    - Correspondence 1985-1986 (Reel 6)
    - Installation 1983 (Reel 6)
    - Newspaper clippings 1983-1984 (Reel 6)
  - Kevin M. Turman 1988
    - Installation 1988 (Reel 6)
- Publications 1913-1989
  (primarily 1927-1989)
  The Publications group comprises three linear feet of materials and is arranged by frequency of publication: annual, periodic, quarterly, and weekly. Annual publications include anniversary publications, and the programs for men's day and women's day. Of interest in the periodic subgroup are the programs for the music recitals and funerals. The music programs provide entry to this crucial aspect of church life, and the funeral publications contain brief obituaries. The quarterly, Second Baptist Advocate, is a well-crafted magazine replete with lengthy articles, photographs of church groups, and local advertising. The collection includes issues of the Advocate from its inception in 1952 to 1981, when it was evidently supplanted by the annual report. Nearly half of the Publications group consists of the weekly bulletins, the Second Baptist Item and the Second Baptist Herald, which run to eighteen linear inches. Unfortunately only two issues of the Item are extant. The Herald provides a weekly chronicle of Second Baptist's services, activities of members and groups, and meetings for the years 1926 through 1989. This remarkably informative source is a fairly complete run week- by-week except for spotty coverage from 1962 to 1975.
  - Annual 1949-1989
    - Anniversary of Second Baptist 1949-1951, 1984-1989 (Reel 6)
    - Men's Day 1952-1988 (Reel 6)
    - Women's Day 1949-1988 (Reel 6)
  - Periodic 1925-1989
    (primarily 1983-1989)
    - Altar Circle 1960-1988 (Reel 6)
    - Cookbook (sesquicentennial) 1986 (Reel 6)
    - Funerals 1946-1989 (Reel 6)
    - Miscellaneous 1925-1989 (Reel 6)
    - Music/Recitals 1927-1950 (Reel 6)
    - Music/Recitals 1951-1988 (Reel 7)
    - Testimonials 1964-1985 (Reel 7)
    - Usher Boards 1947-1987 (Reel 7)
  - Quarterly 1952-1981
    - Second Baptist Advocate, 1952-January 1961 (Reel 7)
    - Second Baptist Advocate, April 1961-1973 (Reel 8)
    - Second Baptist Advocate, 1974-1981 (Reel 9)
  - Weekly 1913-1989 (primarily 1927-1989)
    - The Baptist Item, 1913, 1917 (Reel 9)
    - Second Baptist Herald, 1924-September 30, 1928 (Reel 9)
    - Second Baptist Herald, October 7, 1928-1942 (Reel 10)
    - Second Baptist Herald, 1943-October 20, 1957 (Reel 11)
    - Second Baptist Herald, November 10, 1957-August 27, 1978 (Reel 12)
    - Second Baptist Herald, September 3, 1978-May 27, 1984 (Reel 13)
    - Second Baptist Herald, June 3, 1984-July 23, 1989 (Reel 14)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series, the only non-microfilmed material in the collection, includes a photograph of the church's exterior in 1920, a photograph of a gym class in 1912, and a photograph of servers at a church banquet in 1916.
  - Photographs of church buildings and church activities, 1 folder (Folder 1)